i'd like to welcome people to
introduction to psychology
my name is dr paul bloom and i'm the
professor for this course
uh if you haven't yet picked up
a syllabus from the front of the class
please raise your hand are we out are we
at a
syllabi oh please raise your hand and
when the teaching fellows will bring it
to you if you don't yet have a syllabus
um
the syllabus is also available on this
website this website will become
important to you should you choose to
take this class
it will include the syllabus
which will occasionally be revised
well in advance
also all of the class material will be
on this site including copies of the
slides i'm presenting including these
slides right now
practice exams
and any details on the written
assignments
so you'll need to use this website
regularly
to keep in touch with the course today
will be a short class what i just want
to do today
is orient you tell you what this course
is about
i know this is shopping period and i
want to give you a good sense of what
you'd be in for if you took this course
i want to go over the style of the
classes the evaluation the readings and
so on
and then give some examples of some of
the specific topics that we'll be
covering
but before i get started i have to point
out something a little bit unusual about
this class
we are being filmed
this course is one of seven courses
chosen to begin the yale university open
educational resources video lecture
project
and what this means is that when the
year is over
these videos will be available on the
internet free for anybody who wants to
see them and ideally will be accessed by
people
across many different countries some who
would not normally have access to a
university education
i see this as a good and honorable use
of yale's resources and of course it's
also part of yale's plan for world
domination
so because of this a yale university
production team from the center of media
initiatives is going to be taping all
the class lectures and they're up there
the idea is that this should be as
unobtrusive as possible
and the classroom experience should
essentially be the same as if they're
not there so it's their intention to
tape the lectures to take me and
sometimes uh
the slides but not tape your faces or
voices so we're not having you sign
release forms
um two things one thing is personally
i have to remind myself
not to use profanity because children
may be watching so i'll try not to do
that
there's also another complexity if you
are in the front row
or the second row or the third row it is
possible that some part of your head