i'd like to welcome people to
introduction to psychology
my name is dr paul bloom and i'm the
professor for this course
uh if you haven't yet picked up
a syllabus from the front of the class
please raise your hand are we out are we
at a
syllabi oh please raise your hand and
when the teaching fellows will bring it
to you if you don't yet have a syllabus
um
the syllabus is also available on this
website this website will become
important to you should you choose to
take this class
it will include the syllabus
which will occasionally be revised
well in advance
also all of the class material will be
on this site including copies of the
slides i'm presenting including these
slides right now
practice exams
and any details on the written
assignments
so you'll need to use this website
regularly
to keep in touch with the course today
will be a short class what i just want
to do today
is orient you tell you what this course
is about
i know this is shopping period and i
want to give you a good sense of what
you'd be in for if you took this course
i want to go over the style of the
classes the evaluation the readings and
so on
and then give some examples of some of
the specific topics that we'll be
covering
but before i get started i have to point
out something a little bit unusual about
this class
we are being filmed
this course is one of seven courses
chosen to begin the yale university open
educational resources video lecture
project
and what this means is that when the
year is over
these videos will be available on the
internet free for anybody who wants to
see them and ideally will be accessed by
people
across many different countries some who
would not normally have access to a
university education
i see this as a good and honorable use
of yale's resources and of course it's
also part of yale's plan for world
domination
so because of this a yale university
production team from the center of media
initiatives is going to be taping all
the class lectures and they're up there
the idea is that this should be as
unobtrusive as possible
and the classroom experience should
essentially be the same as if they're
not there so it's their intention to
tape the lectures to take me and
sometimes uh
the slides but not tape your faces or
voices so we're not having you sign
release forms
um two things one thing is personally
i have to remind myself
not to use profanity because children
may be watching so i'll try not to do
that
there's also another complexity if you
are in the front row
or the second row or the third row it is
possible that some part of your head
your back or even your face might end up
on film um
if if you are in the witness protection
program
or you're some sort of fugitive you
probably don't want to sit in the front
row
i'll give them if people want to
unobtrusively kind of slide back that's
that's fine as i'm talking
okay we're ready
so
i'd like to to um welcome people to this
course introduction to psychology my
name is dr paul bloom i'm professor of
this course
and what this is going to be
is a comprehensive introduction to the
study of the human mind
so we're going to cover a very very wide
range of topics
including brains children language sex
memory madness discuss racism and love
and many others we're going to talk
about things like the proper explanation
for differences between men and women
the question of whether animals can
learn language
the puzzle of what grosses us out the
problem of why some of us eat too much
and what we could do to stop
the question of why people go crazy in
groups
research into whether you can trust your
childhood memories
research into why some of us get
depressed and others don't
the style of this is there'll be two
lectures a week
as well as
course readings
now to do well in the course
you have to attend both the lectures and
do the readings there will be some
overlap
in some cases the lectures will be quite
linked to the readings but there will be
some parts of the readings that will not
find your way into lectures and some
lectures some entire lectures that will
not connect at all to the readings
so
to pursue this course properly you have
to do both um what this means is that if
you miss a class you need to get notes
and so you should get them from a friend
or from the person sitting next to you
the slides
are going to be made available online
so one of the things you don't have to
do is you don't have to write this down
you take notes any way you choose but if
you don't get anything on there it'll be
available online i'm going to post it in
a format which will be black and white
and easy to print out so you don't have
to worry about this but again
attending to the slides is not a
substitute for attending class
there's a textbook um peter gray's
psychology fifth edition
and there's also a collection of short
readings the norton reader edited by
gary marcus
it's an excellent textbook it's an
excellent collection and you should get
them both
they're available at labyrinth bookstore
on york street or you can get them
online
i should note that last time i taught
the course i used the marcus reader and
when professor marvin chun taught his
course last semester he used peter
gray's fifth edition textbook so there
may be a lot of used copies floating
around you should feel free to try to
get one of those
the evaluation goes like this
there is a midterm and there's a final
the final will not be held in the exam
period because i like to take long
vacations it will be held the last day
of class
the exams will be will be multiple
choice and short answer fill in the
blank that sort of thing prior to the
exams i will post previous exams online
so you have a feeling for how these
exams work and so on there will also be
review sessions
starting at the beginning of the third
week of class that is not next week but
the week after on monday each monday i'm
going to put up a brief question
or set of questions which you have to
answer
and your answers need to be sent to your
teaching fellow and you'll be given a
teaching fellow a signed one
by friday
this is not meant to be difficult it's
not meant to be more than five ten
minutes of work but the point of the
question
fifteen twenty minutes of work um but
the point of the question is to motivate
people to keep up with the material and
do the readings these questions will be
marked past fail i expect most everybody
to pass all of the questions but it's
just to keep you on track and keep you
going
there's a book review
a short book review to be written
towards near the end of the class i'll
give details about that later on in the
semester and there's also an
experimental participation requirement
and next week i'll i'll hand out a piece
of paper describing the requirement the
point of requirement is to give you all
experience
actually seeing what psychological
research is about as well as to give us
hundreds of subjects to do our
experiments on
um
the issue sometimes comes up as the how
to do well in the course
um here's how to do well
attend all the classes keep up with the
readings ideally keep up with the
readings
before you come to class
and one thing i would strongly suggest
is to form some sort of study groups
either formally or informally have
people you could talk to when the exam
prior to the exams are she's patting
somebody next to to her i hope you know
him
and um
and and and in fact what i'm going to do
not this class because the shopping
period i don't know who's coming next
class or what but i'll set up a few
minutes prior at the beginning class for
people just to introduce themselves to
the person next to them
so they have some sort of resource
in the class
now
this is a large class
and if you don't do anything about it it
can be very anonymous and some of you
may choose to pursue it that way and
it's totally fine but what i would
suggest you do is establish some contact
with us either with me or with any of
the teaching fellows and i'll introduce
the teaching fellows sometime next week
um you could talk to us at the beginning
or the end of class
unless there's special circumstances i
always try to come
at least 10 minutes early and i try and
i'm willing to stay late to talk to
people
you could come by during my office hours
which are on the syllabus and you can
send me email and set up an appointment
i'm very willing to talk to students
about intellectual ideas about course
problems and so on and if you see me at
some point just on campus
you could introduce yourself and i i'd
like to meet people from this class
so again a lot of stress you have the
option of staying anonymous in this
class but you also have the option of
seeking out and making some sort of
contact with us
okay
that's the formal stuff of the course
what's this course about
um unlike a lot of other courses some
people come to intro psychology with
some unusual motivations
um maybe you're crazy
and hope to become less crazy
maybe you want to learn how to study
better improve your sex life interpret
your dreams and win friends and
influence people
those are not necessarily bad reasons to
take
this course and with the exception of
the sex part
this course might actually help you out
with some of these things the study of
scientific psychology has a lot of
insights of real world relevance to real
problems that we face in our everyday
lives and i want to try and when these
issues come up i'm going to try to
stress them and and and make you try to
think about the extent to which the
laboratory research i'll be talking
about can affect your everyday life how
you study how you interact with people
how you might try to persuade somebody
of something else what sort of therapy
works best for you
but the general goals of this course
are actually
i think even more interesting than that
what i want to do is provide a
state-of-the-art introduction to the
most important topic that there is
um
us
how the human mind works how we think
what makes us what we are
and we'll be approaching this from a
range of directions so traditionally
psychology is often broken up into the
following in into five sub areas
neuroscience which is the study of the
of the mind by looking at the brain
developmental which is the area which i
focus mostly on which is trying to learn
about how people develop and grow and
learn
cognitive
which is the one term of the five that
might be unfamiliar to some of you but
it refers to a sort of computational
approach to studying the mind often
viewing the mind on analogy with a
computer and looking at how people do
things like understand language
recognize objects
play games and so on
there is social
which is the study of how people act in
groups how people act with other people
and there is clinical which is maybe the
aspect of psychology that people think
of immediately when they hear psychology
which is a study of mental health and
mental illness
and we'll be covering all of those areas
we'll also be covering a set of related
areas
i am convinced that you cannot study the
mind
solely by looking at the discipline of
psychology discipline psychology spills
over to issues of how the mind has
evolved
economics and game theory
are now an essential tools for
understanding human thought and human
behavior there's issues connecting to
philosophy computer science anthropology
literature theology and many many other
domains
so this course will be wide-ranging in
that sense
um at this point i've been speaking in
generalities so
i want to close this introductory class
by giving five examples
of the sorts of topics we'll be covering
and i'll start the topic that we'll be
covering next week on monday
the brain
um this is a brain
in fact it's a specific person's brain
and what's interesting about the brain
is that little white mark there
it's her brain
it's terri schiavo's brain
you recognize her more from pictures
like that
and what a case like this where somebody
um
is is
in a coma is without consciousness
as a result of damage to the brain is a
stark illustration of the physical
nature of mental life
the physical basis for everything that
we normally hold dear like free will
consciousness
morality and emotions
and that's what we'll begin the course
with talking about how a physical thing
can give rise to mental life
we'll talk a lot about children
this is actually a specific child it's
uh my son zachary my younger son um
dressed up as super as spider-man but it
is halloween no it's not halloween oh
no
there's more to say about that um
i study child development for a living
and i'm interested in several questions
so one question is just a question of
development everybody in this room
can speak and understand english
everybody in this room has some
understanding of how the world works how
physical things behave everybody in this
room has some understanding of other
people and how people behave
and the question
that that preoccupies developmental
psychologists is how do we come to have
this knowledge
and in particular how much of it is
hardwired built in innate and how much
of it is a product of culture
of of language of schooling
and developmental psychologists use
many ingenious methods to try to pull
these apart
and and try to figure out what what as
what's what's
what are the basic components of human
nature
there's also the question of continuity
to what extent is zachary at that age
going to be
that way forever
to what extent is your fate sealed
to what extent could if i were to meet
you when you were five years old
i could describe the way you are now
the poet
william wordsworth
wrote
the child is father to the man
and what this means is that you can see
within every child the adult he or she
will become
we will look and and ask the question
whether this is true is it true for your
personality is it true for your interest
is it true for your intelligence
another question having to do with
development
is
what makes us the way we are
we're different in a lot of ways
the people in this room differ according
to
their taste and food they differ
according to their iqs whether they're
aggressive or shy
whether they're attracted to males
females both or neither whether
whether they're good at music
whether
they're politically liberal or
conservative
why are we different what's the
explanation for why we're different
and again this could be translated in
terms of a question of genes and
environment to what extent are things
the result of the genes we possess to
what extent are our our individual
nature as a result of how we were raised
and to what extent are they best
explained in terms of an interaction um
one common theory for instance is that
we are shaped by our parents
um this was best summarized most
famously by the british poet phillip
larkin
who wrote
they they messed you up
your mum and dad
they may not mean to but they do
they fill you with the faults they had
and add some extra just for you
is he right
it's very controversial you it's been a
series of a huge controversy in a
popular culture to the extent to which
parents matter
and this is an issue which will
preoccupy us for much of the course
a different question what makes somebody
attractive
and this can be asked at all sorts of
levels but a symbol level is
what makes for a pretty face
so these are
according to ratings very attractive
faces
they are not the faces of real people
what's on the screen are computer
generated faces
um of a caucasian male and a caucasian
female who don't exist in the real world
but through using this sort of computer
generation and then asking people what
they think of this face what they think
of that face scientists have come to
some sense as to what really makes a
face attractive
both within cultures and across cultures
and that's something which we're going
to devote some time to when we talk
about social behavior and in particular
when we talk about sex
not all attractiveness not all beauty of
course is linked to sex
so
so pandas for instance like this panda
are notoriously cute
and i don't
i don't have anything to say about it
really it's just a cute picture
um morality
is extremely
central to our lives
and a deep question which we will
struggle with throughout most of the
course is the question of good and evil
evil and good um these three pictures
exemplify different sorts of of evil
what you call institutional evil
um by somebody um
behaving cruelly or towards somebody for
somebody else perhaps not due to malice
but because of the situation that she's
in it has a picture of osama bin laden
a mass murderer driven by political
cause and then there's this guy on the
bottom anybody know who he is
ted bundy who got that
film that man no
ted bundy
exactly and that's like
before we get into the technicals that's
like crazy evil
and and and we're going to have to come
to terms
with why some people are like that
and again the same situation comes up is
it part of your nature
to be good or bad um
or is it largely due to the situation
that you that you've fallen
and there's a lot of some
quite spectacular experiments that try
to tease that
apart um if we're going to talk about
evil we should also talk about good
um
this is these are pictures of um of two
notoriously good men
um oscar schindler and paul russessa but
each who at different times in history
saved the lives of many many people at
great risk to themselves
schindler and the holocaust um and and
and then the other guy in
in um could i can't pronounce his name
recessive again
in rwanda
and they both had real good movies made
about them
um
and and so but what's interesting with
these cases is you couldn't have
predicted ahead of time
that they would be heroes
and one personal issue within any of us
is what would we do
in such situations
finally
throughout this course
we will discuss mental illness
now
towards the end of the class i want to
devote a full week
to discussing major or disorders like
depression and anxiety
because of their profound social
importance
such disorders are reasonably common in
college students
many people in this room are currently
suffering from a mood disorder an
anxiety disorder or both
and i won't ask for a show of hands but
i know a lot of people in this room are
on some form of medication for this
disorder
um and we'll discuss we'll discuss the
current research and why people get
these disorders and what's the best way
to make them better
but i also have a weakness
for the less common mental disorders
that i think tell us something really
interesting about mental life
so when we talk about memory for
instance we'll talk about disorders in
memory including some disorders that
keep you from forming new memories as
well as or disorders of amnesia where
you forget the past and these are
extraordinarily interesting for all
sorts of reasons
early in the course in fact i think next
week
we will discuss no later on in the
course the middle of middle of the
semester we will discuss the amazing
case of phineas gage
phineas gage was a construction worker
about 100 years ago
due to an explosion a metal pipe went
through his head like so
miraculously he was not killed
in fact
his friends it went through his head
when ended up a hundred feet away
covered with brains and blood
and phineas gays sat down and oh
and then on the way to the hospital they
stopped by a pub
have some cider
he was not blind he was not deaf he was
not
but something else happened to him
he lost his sense of right and wrong
he lost his control
he used to be a hard-working family man
after an accident he lost all of that
he couldn't hold a job he couldn't stay
faithful to his wife
he couldn't speak for five minutes
without cursing
he got into fights he got into brawls he
got drunk he lost his control
he ended up on a circus sideshow
traveling through the country with the
big steel pipe that went through his
head
and this is again
an extraordinary example of how the the
brain can give rise to the mind and how
things that go wrong the brain can
affect you in in a serious way
we'll discuss
cases of multiple personality disorder
where people have more than one
personality and also discuss the debate
over what's whether such cases are true
or not whether they can be taken as a
real phenomena or a made-up phenomena
which is there's a matter of a lot of
controversy and then we'll even discuss
some rarer cases
like cap grass syndrome
cup grass syndrome is typically is is
there's hundreds of cases not many
hundreds of cases it's typically the
result of some sort of stroke
and what happens to you is very specific
you develop a particular
delusion
like it's getting dark
and
the delusion
is that the people you love the most
have been replaced
they've been replaced by aliens or
robots
thank you um by by
by martians by cia agents by trained
actors and actresses but the people
but the idea is the people you care for
the most you believe are gone
and
this could lead to tragic consequences
cop grass syndrome is associated with a
very high level of violence
one man in australia a couple of years
ago was under the delusion that his
father was replaced with a robot and cut
off his head
a related disorder
involving the very same parts of the
brain
is called katard's syndrome and katarn
syndrome is you believe that you're dead
you believe that you're dead you you are
persuaded that you're dead you're
walking around you know you're walking
around you know you that there are
people around um but you think that
you're dead
and what's striking about these is it's
not these are not just sort of big
screwy problems of messed up people
rather they're located they're related
at a pinpoint level
to certain parts of your brain
and we're going to talk about the best
modern theories as to why these
syndromes occur
now
the reason to be interested in them
again is not because they're frequent
they aren't and it's not because of some
sort of gruesome morbid curiosity rather
by looking at extreme cases
they can help us best understand
normal life
often by looking at extremes it throws
into sharp contrast things we naturally
take for granted the issue of
psychopathy
of people who either do the brain damage
or because they're born that way have no
moral understanding can help us
cope with questions of free will and
responsibility of the relationship or
difference between mental illness and
evil multiple personality cases force us
to address the question of what is a
self
what to what extent do are all of us
composed of multiple people
and to what extent are we a single
unified person over time cases like cop
grass
are important because they tell us about
how we see the world they tell us for
instance that there's a difference
between recognizing something in a sense
that you could name it
and knowing what it is
and and and so by studying these
abnormal cases we get some insight into
regular life
so that's the end of the illustration of
the example topics
the syllabus lists many more
i'll end by telling you
that
there's a there's a lot of stuff that
we'll be talking about that i want to
talk about that i am not expert in
and fortunately um there is a community
at yale of the best scholars and
teachers on the planet
and so it would be a shame for me not to
use them
to cover some of these issues and so i'm
going to have include
four guest lectures
the first one is dr marvin chun
who is teaches the introduction
psychology course
in the fall and is my competition
and he's going to give an amazing
lecture on cognitive neuroscience
especially the cognitive neuroscience of
faces
dr susan nolan huxima
is the world's authority on depression
and in particular on sex differences in
depression and she's going to talk about
this towards the end of the course
kelly brownell
is going to talk is the head of the rudd
center
focuses on obesity eating disorders
dieting and he'll talk about the
psychology of food
and finally
dr peter salovey dean of yale college is
going to come to us on valentine's day
and tell us
everything he knows about the mysteries
of love
all of these details are in the syllabus
um and i'll stick around and answer
questions hope to see you next week